Guide to the Mount Vernon Seminary and College Commencement Collection, 1877-1999 MVC0037.MS
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Mount Vernon Seminary and College Commencement Collection
1877-1999
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Pelham, Peter
Mount Vernon Seminary
Mount Vernon College
MVC0037.MS
6 Linear Feet
This collection contains programs, invitations, correspondence, speeches and addresses, memoranda, notes, personal files, and photographs. The materials date from 1877 to 2000. These are the commencement, baccalaureate, convocation, and other special event programs and files of Mount Vernon College, which includes Mount Vernon Seminary, Mount Vernon Junior College, and Mount Vernon Preparatory School. This collection includes personal files of Mount Vernon College Presidents, Peter D. Pelham, Victoria Schuck, and M. Jane Evans, from 1968-1987.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Arrangement
Organized into 2 series: Commencement and baccalaureate programs and Presidential Office commencement planning files.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains programs, invitations, correspondence, speeches and addresses, memoranda, notes, personal files, newspaper clippings, playbills, class songs, and photographs. The materials date from 1877 to 2000. These are the commencement, baccalaureate, convocation, and other special event programs and files of Mount Vernon College, which includes Mount Vernon Seminary, Mount Vernon Junior College, and Mount Vernon Preparatory School. Programs from most years between 1877-1999 are represented, which include lists of the graduates in each class year. This collection includes personal files of Mount Vernon College Presidents, Peter D. Pelham, Victoria Schuck, and M. Jane Evans, from 1968-1987, relating to commencement and other event planning, which were maintained in the Presidential Office of the College.
Biographical / Historical
The Mount Vernon Seminary was officially established by Elizabeth Somers in 1875; she named it after her brother's church in Baltimore, Mount Vernon Place Methodist. The Seminary began as a six year preparatory school, with four years of high school level classes, and two years of post-high school curriculum, calling it a "Family and Day School for Young Ladies." In order to graduate, students had to complete a formal process of "Senior Essays" in which they completed primary research and wrote on a current political or social topic, including such provocative issues as child labor, prohibition, poverty, and women's suffrage. In the 1920 graduating class, eight women continued their education at universities such as the University of Wisconsin, Stanford, Northwestern and the University of Texas; by 1923 graduates were going to such other prestigious universities as UC-Berkeley, Columbia, Cornell, Smith College and the University of Chicago. Such advancements in higher education were uncommon for women of the day, but Mount Vernon was one of the premier preparatory institutions in the country.
In 1927, Mount Vernon established a Junior College, and with its establishment, students no longer had to complete six years of courses to receive a diploma; they graduated from the Seminary after four years and could continue on to the Junior College for two more years of college preparation. After World War II began, the U.S. Navy took over the campus as a part of the war effort; in 1945 the school purchased 21 acres on Foxhall Road and surrounding areas, and had applied for accreditation to award Associates of Arts Degrees after completing two years of the Junior College.
Despite its expansion, by 1965 the Board of Trustees voted unanimously to dissolve the Seminary by 1969, as it could not financially support both institutions. During the 1960s, the Junior College developed new academic concentrations such as government, international relations and political science to reflect its location in the nation's capital. At the same time, it began to phase out its vocational training such as home economics and secretarial skills to make room for these higher education courses.
By 1973, the Board of Higher Education licensed the college to award Bachelor of Arts (BA) degrees such as Public Affairs, Government, Business Administration, Childhood, Special Education, and the Visual Arts, as well as honorary Doctor of Humane Letters and Juris Doctor Degrees; in 1976, the college received initial accreditation as a four-year college and was reaccredited ten years later. However, by 1996 the college announced a plan to affiliate with George Washington University; in 1999 the last class of Mount Vernon College graduated. Today, as an affiliated campus of GWU, Mount Vernon offers special living accommodations, as well as learning and leadership programs for female students.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Collection acquired by GWU upon merger with Mount Vernon College. Collection transferred to Foggy Bottom campus in 2009.
Bib#
8588728
Women -- Education; Commencement ceremonies -- Washington (D.C.); Women's colleges
- Commencement and baccalaureate programs, 1877-1999; 1871-1999; Series 1; 3.5 Linear Feet
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically by academic year and by school, i.e. MVS (Mount Vernon Seminary), MVJC (Mount Vernon Junior College), MVPS (Mount Vernon Preparatory School), MVC (Mount Vernon College).
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains programs, invitations, schedules, notes, videos and photographs. The materials date from 1877 to 2000. These are the commencement, baccalaureate, convocation, and other special event programs and records of Mount Vernon College, which includes Mount Vernon Seminary, Mount Vernon Junior College, and Mount Vernon Preparatory School. Programs from most years between 1877-1999 are represented, which include lists of the graduates in each class year.
  - MVS Commencement Programs and Invitations (Copies), 1878-1885; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General
    Copies of deaccessioned items and of fragile items within box.
  - MVS Invitations to Graduation Exercises, 1888-1944; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - MVS Invitations to Graduation Exercises, 1953-1969; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Commencement Programs, 1877-1884; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Graduating Exercises, 1888-1892; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Graduating Exercises, 1894-1902; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Graduating Exercises, 1903-1907; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Graduating Exercises, 1908-1915; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Graduating Exercises, 1916-1930; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Graduating Exercises, 1933-1942; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Graduating Exercises, 1943-1944; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Graduating Exercises, 1946-1949; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Graduating Exercises, 1950-1953; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Graduating Exercises, 1954-1957; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Graduating Exercises, 1958-1960; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Graduating Exercises, 1961-1964; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Graduating Exercises, 1965-1966; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Graduating Exercises and Schedules, 1949-1969; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - MVS Baccalaureate Programs, 1928-1941; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - MVS Baccalaureate Programs, 1944-1949; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - MVPS Closing Exercises and Invitation, 1934-1935; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - MVPS Graduation Exercises, 1938-1940; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - MVJC Graduation Exercises, 1948-1949; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - MVJC Graduating Exercises, 1950-1953; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - MVJC Graduating Exercises, 1954-1957; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - MVJC Graduating Exercises, 1958-1961; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - MVJC Graduating Exercises, 1962-1964; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - MVJC Commencement Week Programs, 1953-1968; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - MVJC Commencement, 1965-1967; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - MVJC Commencement, 1968-1969; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - MVJC Commencement Order of Procession, 1961; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - MVJC Baccalaureate Services, 1950-1955; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - MVJC Baccalaureate Services, 1956-1960; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - MVJC Baccalaureate Services, 1961-1965; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - MVJC Baccalaureate Services, 1966-1969; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - MVC Invitations to Graduation Exercises, 1987-1999; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - MVC Commencement, 1970-1973; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - MVC Commencement Order of Procession, 1974; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - MVC Commencement, 1974-1977; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - MVC Commencement, 1978-1979; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - MVC Commencement, 1980-1983; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - MVC Commencement, 1984-1989; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - MVC Commencement, 1990-1994; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - MVC Commencement, 1995-1997; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - MVC Commencement, 1999; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - MVC Baccalaureate, 1979-1999; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - MVC Convocation Programs, 1976-1995; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - MVC Inaugeration of Jane Evans, 7th President of MVC, 1981; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - MVS/MVJC/MVC Founder's Day Programs and Invitations, 1947-1994; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - MVS/MVC Student Organizations and Events, 1903-1996; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    This folder includes items not directly relating to commencement, including playbills, the alumnae song, and invitations and programs from student events.
  - MVC Alumnae Association Video Gift Letter, 2000; Series 1 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - The 124th Graduating Class of Mount Vernon College 1999, Series 1 (Box 7, Videocassette 1)
    Class of 1999 memory video of pictures of the campus, professors, and students.
  - Mount Vernon College 124th Commencement May 16, 1999, Series 1 (Box 7, Videocassette 2)
    Video of the Commencement Ceremony. Loss of audio during 2 minute portion of tape near 1:24:00 present on all copies.
  - Mount Vernon College 124th Commencement May 16, 1999, Series 1 (Box 7, Videocassette 3)
- Presidential Office commencement planning files, 1968-1987; 1971-1987; Series 2; Pelham, Peter; Mount Vernon College; Evans, Marilyn Jane Coutant; Schuck, Victoria; Lloyd, George; Ford, Gerald R. (1913-2006); 2.5 Linear Feet Mount Vernon Seminary Presidential Office Commencement Planning Files
  Arranged chronologically. Files labeled with quotation marks maintain original title of file, as given by the President's Office.
  This series contains programs, invitations, correspondence, speeches and addresses, memoranda, notes, personal files, seating charts and schedules, newspaper and magazine articles, and photographs. The materials date from 1968 to 1987. These are the commencement, baccalaureate, convocation, inaugeration, and other special event files of Mount Vernon College which were maintained in the Presidential Office of the College. This series includes personal files of Mount Vernon College Presidents, Peter D. Pelham, Victoria Schuck, and M. Jane Evans, relating to commencement and other event planning. Includes correspondence from such notable people as, President Richard Nixon, President Gerald R. Ford, Marjorie Day, Barbara Walters, and many notable senators, representatives, college presidents, scholars, faculty, and alumnae. Much of this correspondence is related to selecting a speaker for commencement ceremonies or the awarding of honorary degrees.
  Women -- Education; Planning; Women's colleges; Commencement ceremonies -- Washington (D.C.)
  - MVC "Commencement Speaker 1968" Photo of Dr. Kuhns and Frank Farmer at Commencement, Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - MVC "Commencement Speaker 1968" Photos of Cecil and Cynthia Beasley at Prep Commencement, Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - MVC "Convocation 1971-73", 1971-1973; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - MVC "Commencement and Baccalaureate 1973", Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - MVC "Commencement 1974" (Part 1 of 2), Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    Original folder from Presidential Office has been split into two folders, owing to size.
  - MVC "Commencement 1974" (Part 2 of 2), Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - MVC "Convocation 1974", Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - MVC "Convocation 1975", Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - MVC "Commencement 1975", Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - MVC "Fall Convocation '76", 1976; Series 2 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - MVC "Commencement and Baccalaureate 1976", Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - MVC "Commencement 1977: May 29, 1977" (Part 1 of 2), Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    Original file from President's Office has been split into two parts due to size.
  - MVC "Commencement 1977: May 29, 1977" (Part 2 of 2), Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - MVC " Convocation 1977 (First Convocation of Dr. Schuck)", Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - MVC "Commencement May 28, 1978", Series 2 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - MVC "Inaugeration of Dr. Schuck" (Part 1 of 2), 1978; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    Original file from President's Office split into 2 parts due to size.
  - MVC "Inaugeration of Dr. Schuck" (Part 2 of 2), 1978; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - MVC "Convocation: September 13, 1978", Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - MVC "Convocation 1979 Dr. Victoria Schuck", Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - MVC "Convocation Reception 9/8/79", 1979; Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - MVC "Commencement File 1979", Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - MVC "Commencement- 1979: Dr. Victoria Schuck" (Part 1 of 2), Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - MVC "Commencement- 1979: Dr Victoria Schuck" (Part 2 of 2), Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    Original file has been separated into two parts.
  - MVC "Convocation 1980", Series 2 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - MVC "Commencement: Victoria Schuck 1980", Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - MVC "Convocation 1980 President's Office Gillian" (Part 1 of 2), Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    Original file has been separated into two parts due to size.
  - MVC "Convocation 1980 President's Office Gillian" (Part 2 of 2), Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - MVC "Commencement MJE", 1980-1981; Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - MVC "Materials for Inaugeral Address/ 1981 Misc.", Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - MVC "Commencement 1981", Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - MVC: "Dr. Jane Evans- Speeches", circa 1981; Series 2 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - MVC "Commencement 1982", Series 2 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - MVC "Convocation 1982", Series 2 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - MVC "Convocation 1982", Series 2 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - MVC "Convocation 1982" Photos, Series 2 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - MVC Commencement Files "Convocation 1982" Photos, Series 2 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - MVC "Commencement 1982", Series 2 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - MVC "Convocation 1982: Program Samples Included", Series 2 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - MVC Presidential Office Commencement Files, 1982-1983; Series 2 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - MVC "Commencement 1983", Series 2 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - MVC Presidential Office Commencement Files, 1983-1984; Series 2 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - MVC Presidential Office Commencement Files: Programs, 1983-1986; Series 2 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - MVC "Convocation 1984", Series 2 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - MVC Presidential Office Commencement Files, 1986; Series 2 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - MVC "Special Events- Commencement 1987", Series 2 (Box 12, Folder 14)